Guide to the Crown Heights History Project collection 1994.006
Brooklyn Historical Society
Crown Heights History Project collection
1993-1994
1993
Brooklyn Historical Society
Brooklyn Historical Society (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
1994.006
76.31 Gigabytes in 247 files, total running time: 38 hours, 7 minutes, 56 seconds; 3.31 linear feet in 1 record box, 3 document boxes, 2 flat boxes
Oral Histories include recordings collected through the Crown Heights History Project, undertaken by a partnership of cultural institutions led by Brooklyn Historical Society (BHS) in 1993. The recordings contain over forty voices with perspectives on the racial tensions and discrimination that preceded three days of violence and unrest in the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn in 1991, the actions of the police, city government and mass media during the crisis, and the forms of reconciliation in the succeeding months. Among the narrators are Jamaican Americans, Guyanese Americans, Lubavitcher Jewish Americans, Reformed Jewish Americans, descendants of European and Russian Jews, and African Americans with roots in the Southern United States.
Box 1994.006
Box Unprocessed 1 of 5
Box Unprocessed 2 of 5
Box Unprocessed 3 of 5
Box Unprocessed 4 of 5
Box Unprocessed 5 of 5
Box 1 of 5
Box 2 of 5
Box 3 of 5
Box 4 of 5
Box 5 of 5
Box 6
Biographical / Historical
History of Crown Heights: From the late nineteenth century up to the World War I era, the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn was known for being an upper and upper middle class residential enclave. Russian Jews, Irish, and Italians moved there as a part of the boom in immigration from 1880 to 1940. Smaller migrations to Crown Heights occurred as well, with Caribbean migrants among these. Seeing an opportunity for first-time home ownership, some of Harlem's African American residents moved to the neighborhood in the 1930s. A great wave of Caribbean immigration occurred in the 1960s and 1970s, and with many White residents removing to the suburbs, those immigrants along with Caribbean Americans and African Americans made up a great majority of the population from the 1960s to the 1990s. The Lubavitcher Hasidim, a Judaic movement that established its headquarters in Crown Heights in 1940, accounted for about eight percent of the population, according to early 1990s figures.*
In 1991, long simmering tensions between members of the Lubavitch Hasidim community and Black community erupted in neighborhood unrest and violence. That August, a car driven by Yosef Lifish of the Lubavitch Hasidim, struck Gavin Cato, a Guyanese American boy, along with his cousin. Cato died at the scene. Within hours and a few blocks away, a mob attack and stabbing of Yankel Rosenbaum, an Australian rabbinical student, was instigated by an African American man, Charles Price, and committed by a Carribbean American teen, Lemrick Nelson. Rosenbaum later succumbed to his wounds, and the resulting three days of strife was encapsulated as the "Crown Heights Riot" by the news media.
The Crown Heights History Project at Brooklyn Historical Society: Two years after the Crown Heights Riot, Brooklyn Historical Society (BHS), Brooklyn Children's Museum, and the Society for the Preservation of Weeksville and Bedford-Stuyvesant History started a collaborative project to examine the subtle community disconnects prior to August of 1991, the feelings and meanings of the flashpoint events, and the existential unease and healing movements in the communities afterwards. "Bridging Eastern Parkway" was the tentative title for the mounting of exhibitions at all three institutions. Cultural anthropologist Jill Vexler and historian Craig Wilder conducted research and interviews with the Crown Heights neighborhood residents and then curated the exhibitions. Collectively retitled the "Crown Heights History Project" in late 1993, BHS went on to present "Crown Heights: Perceptions and Realities" in 1994. Brooklyn Children's Museum presented "Crown Heights: The Inside Scoop" and the Society for the Preservation of Weeksville presented "Crown Heights: The African Diaspora." Oral history interviews, conducted by Vexler and Wilder, with assistance from Aviva Segall, made up a substantial component of the exhibition preparation and exhibited materials.
*Rule, Sheila. "The Voices and Faces of Crown Heights." New York Times (New York, NY), April 15, 1994.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains oral history recordings and transcripts, as well as exhibition materials, from Brooklyn Historical Society's Crown Heights History Project, also known as "Bridging Eastern Parkway." Crown Heights History Project oral histories include audio and transcripts created and collected within the context of an exhibition project undertaken in part by BHS in 1993 and 1994. Three interviewers recorded conversations with over forty narrators. In addition to exhibition product value, the oral histories were conducted as life history and community anthropology interviews; topics of discussion include family and heritage, immigration and relocation, cultural and racial relations, occupations and professions, education and religion, housing and gentrification, civil unrest and reconciliation, media representation and portrayal, and activism. The series of exhibition research materials document the outreach efforts for interviews and materials from the community as well as exhibition scripts and curatorial notes.
Arrangement
The described series of oral histories as well as an unprocessed series of exhibition files comprise the Crown Heights History Project collection. Oral histories and transcripts were kept in their original order, largely arranged alphabetically by the narrator's last name. Exhibition files have not yet been processed.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers with varied restrictions according to narrator agreement. Many oral histories can be accessed onsite at the Brooklyn Historical Society's Othmer Library and online on the Oral History Portal. Unprocessed exhibition research materials are open to researchers upon request and are accessible onsite at the Othmer Library.
Related Materials
In addition to this collection, Brooklyn Historical Society has oral history collections and other records related to the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn:
- The West Indian Carnival Documentation Project Records includes thirty-four interviews dating from 1994 to 1995 (2010.019)
- The Listen to this: Crown Heights Oral History collection includes forty-three interviews conducted in 2010 (2010.020)
- Eastern Parkway Coalition records, 1952-2007 (2007.016)
- 959 Park Place Tenants' Association records (1978.009)
For more information on these collections please visit our online finding aid portal at Brooklyn Historical Society.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Recordings and transcripts were collected through the Crown Heights History Project, undertaken by a partnership of cultural institutions led by Brooklyn Historical Society (BHS) in 1993.The curator of the project, Jill Vexler, retained the project records. Brooklyn Historical Society acquired the collection from Ms. Vexler in 2012.
Oral History note
Oral history interviews are intimate conversations between two people, both of whom have generously agreed to share these recordings with the Brooklyn Historical Society archives and with researchers. Please listen in the spirit with which these were shared. Researchers will understand that: 1. The Brooklyn Historical Society abides by the General Principles & Best Practices for Oral History as agreed upon by the Oral History Association (2009) and expects that use of this material will be done with respect for these professional ethics. 2. Every oral history relies on the memories, views and opinions of the narrator. Because of the personal nature of oral history, listeners may find some viewpoints or language of the recorded participants to be objectionable. In keeping with its mission of preservation and unfettered access whenever possible, BHS presents these views as recorded. 3. Transcripts created prior to 2008 serve as a guide to the interview and are not considered verbatim. The audio recording should be considered the primary source for each interview. It may contain natural false starts, verbal stumbles, misspeaks, repetitions that are common in conversation, and other passages and phrases omitted from the transcript. This decision was made because BHS gives primacy to the audible voice and also because some researchers do find useful information in these verbal patterns. 4. Unless these verbal patterns are germane to your scholarly work, when quoting from this material researchers are encouraged to correct the grammar and make other modifications maintaining the flavor of the narrator's speech while editing the material for the standards of print.
Oral history interviews are intimate conversations between two people, both of whom have generously agreed to share these recordings with the Brooklyn Historical Society archives and with researchers. Please listen in the spirit with which these were shared. Researchers will understand that:
1. The Brooklyn Historical Society abides by the General Principles & Best Practices for Oral History as agreed upon by the Oral History Association (2009) and expects that use of this material will be done with respect for these professional ethics.
2. Every oral history relies on the memories, views and opinions of the narrator. Because of the personal nature of oral history, listeners may find some viewpoints or language of the recorded participants to be objectionable. In keeping with its mission of preservation and unfettered access whenever possible, BHS presents these views as recorded.
3. Transcripts created prior to 2008 serve as a guide to the interview and are not considered verbatim. The audio recording should be considered the primary source for each interview. It may contain natural false starts, verbal stumbles, misspeaks, repetitions that are common in conversation, and other passages and phrases omitted from the transcript. This decision was made because BHS gives primacy to the audible voice and also because some researchers do find useful information in these verbal patterns.
4. Unless these verbal patterns are germane to your scholarly work, when quoting from this material researchers are encouraged to correct the grammar and make other modifications maintaining the flavor of the narrator's speech while editing the material for the standards of print.
Historical note bibliography
Conaway, Carol B. "Crown Heights: Politics and Press Coverage of the Race War That Wasn't," Polity 32 (Autumn 1991): 93-118.
Girgenti, Richard H. A Report to the Governor on the Disturbances in Crown Heights: An Assessment of the City's Preparedness and Response to Civil Disorder 2 vols. Albany: New York State Division of Criminal Justice Services, 1993.
Glaberson, William. "Judge Accepts a Guilty Plea in '91 Crown Heights unrest." New York Times (New York, NY), April 13, 2002.
Goldschmidt, Henry. Race and Religion Among the Chosen Peoples of Crown Heights New Brunswick, NJ: Rutgers University Press, 2006.
Gregor, Alison. "Crown Heights, Brooklyn, Where Stoop Life Still Thrives." New York Times. (New York, NY), June 17, 2015.
McCarthy, Sheryl. "Crown Heights Question: What About Charles Price?" Newsday. (Melville, NY), January 9, 2002.
McFarland, Stephen & Nelson, Katie "Timeline: How Crown Heights Riots Unfolded." New York Daily News. (New York, NY), August 14, 2011.
Shapiro, Edward S. Crown Heights: Blacks, Jews, and the 1991 Brooklyn Riot Waltham, MA: Brandeis University Press, 2006.
Waldrep, Christopher. Racial Violence on Trial: A Handbook with Cases, Laws and Documents Santa Barbara: ABC-CLIO, 2001.
African American neighborhoods -- New York (State) -- Kings County; African Americans |x Relations with Jews; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Caribbean Americans; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Exhibition records; Home ownership |x Social aspects |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Immigrants -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Interviews (sound recordings); Jewish neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Judaism |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Multiculturalism; Oral histories (document genres); Race identity; Race relations -- United States; Riots |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Transcripts; United States |x Emigration and immigration; Cato, Gavin; Congregation Lubavitch (Crown Heights, New York, N.Y.); Rosenbaum, Yankel; Schneerson, Menachem Mendel
- Crown Heights History Project oral histories, 1993 to 1994; 1993; 76.31 Gigabytes
  - Asramon, Afealliah, 1993 August 22; 1994.006.01
    Conditions Governing Access and Use
    Access to this oral history is restricted by the donor. Please contact library@brooklynhistory.org for further questions.
    Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Asramon, Afealliah
  - Bernard, A.R., 1993 August 12; 1994.006.02
    Biographical / Historical
    Rev. Dr. A.R. Bernard was born in Panama City, Panama, in 1953. At the age of four, he and his mother, an Olympic track star, immigrated to the United States. Rev. Bernard grew up in the Bedford-Stuyvesant and Bushwick neighborhoods of Brooklyn, where he attended public schools. He was bused to Ridgewood in the 1960s in order to attend junior high and high school. Impacted by the racism and segregation he experienced, Rev. Bernard became interested in the Black Panthers and a follower of the Nation of Islam. On January 11, 1975 he became a Christian. At the time of the interview in 1993, he was ministering to 625 families from the Brooklyn neighborhood of Crown Heights. Focused on a conservative, family centered, practical faith, Rev. Bernard is, as of 2015, the senior pastor of the Christian Cultural Center located at 1400 Linden Boulevard, Brooklyn, New York.
    Scope and Contents
    In the interview, the narrator discusses his childhood in Brooklyn, experience of the Civil Rights Movement, the Nation of Islam and his reasons for converting to Christianity. He remembers racial conflicts, violence and the institutional segregation of the 1950s and '60s. He reflects on the black awareness that the Black Panthers and the Nation of Islam provided in the community during this period and relates this to his conversion experience. The end of the interview focuses on the mission, makeup and contributions of the Christian Life Center. He shares his viewpoints on the breakdown of the family and the community, providing solutions based on the church's focus. He responds to questions concerning the riot of 1991 in the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn. Interview conducted by Craig Wilder.
    Access to the interview is available onsite at the Brooklyn Historical Society's Othmer Library. Use of the oral histories other than for private study, scholarship, or research requires the permission of BHS. For assistance, contact library@brooklynhistory.org.
    African American neighborhoods -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Big churches; Bushwick (New York, N.Y.); Conversion |x Christianity; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Immigrants -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Jewish neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Panamanian Americans; Race identity; School integration |z New York (State); Christian Cultural Center; Bernard, A.R., Rev. Dr.
  - Burston, Chaim, 1993 August 23; 1994.006.03
    Chaim Burston was born to Jewish-American parents in Pasadena, California. After enrolling at Tel Aviv University, Chaim traveled to Israel. Subsequent to joining a Lubavitch Hasidic community as a baal teshuvah (a Jew returning to Orthodoxy), Burston returned to the United States to continue his studies in New York. It was in the Lubavitch community of Crown Heights, Brooklyn where he met his wife Chana. The young couple married, purchased a home – and with Chaim becoming an elementary school teacher along the way – had eight children together. A musician, Burston had taken to playing melodies intended to accompany prayers.
    Burston recounts his youth, travelling abroad to Israel and rediscovering his ancestral religion. He also discusses meeting his wife, what it's like raising a large family in New York City, and touches on relations with his Afro-Caribbean neighbors in the aftermath of the 1991 riot in the Brooklyn neighborhood of Crown Heights. The interview ends with Burston playing his synthesizer keyboard. Interview conducted by Jill Vexler.
    Access to the interview is available onsite at the Brooklyn Historical Society's Othmer Library and online on the Oral History Portal. Use of the oral histories other than for private study, scholarship, or research requires the permission of BHS. For assistance, contact library@brooklynhistory.org.
    African American neighborhoods -- New York (State) -- Kings County; African Americans |x Relations with Jews; California; Caribbean Americans -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Education; Holocaust, Jewish (1939-1945); Immigrants; Israel; Jewish neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Judaism |x Hasidic rite; Musicians; Reformed Judaism; Theology; Congregation Lubavitch (Crown Heights, New York, N.Y.); Burston, Chaim
  - Cattan, Rachel Lea, August 15, 1993; 1994.006.04
    Rachel Lea Cattan was born to Polish parents in Novosibirsk, Siberia in the former Soviet Union. At the age of eleven, her parents moved the family to Lodz, Poland and a year later to Braslav. Then, at age thirteen, the family immigrated to the United States; finally settling in the East New York neighborhood of Brooklyn. Cattan attended New York public schools, including Music and Art High School (Fiorella H. LaGuardia High School). She completed her undergraduate degree, in painting, at Pratt Institute. At the time of the interview in 1993, she was a public school teacher, in the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn, and a divorced mother of four. She is Jewish and has an older sister and a younger brother.
    In the interview, Cattan discusses her childhood; immigration to the United States; her transition to an observant Jewish lifestyle; her divorce; and the racial tensions of the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn. Interview conducted by Aviva Segall.
    This interview is restricted.
    Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); East New York (New York, N.Y.); Identification (Religion); Jews |x Return to Orthodox Judaism; Jews |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Jews, Polish; Jews, Russian; Poland; Riots |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Russia; United States |x Emigration and immigration; Cato, Gavin; Schneerson, Menachem Mendel
  - Crawford, Avroham (Avrohom), 1993 August 24; 1994.006.05
    Avroham Crawford grew up in the Sunset Park neighborhood of Brooklyn, the son of Irish-Catholic immigrants from Newfoundland. He was raised in the church, but considered converting to Judaism while studying for his bachelor's degree in philosophy at NYU (where he continued to work as a librarian through the time of this interview). He moved to the Brooklyn neighborhood of Crown Heights in 1970, and shortly afterwards was converted to Orthodox Judaism with assistance from Rabbi Yisroel Jacobson; he chose the Jewish name "Avroham" at this time. In 1975, he married Suri (Perlman), and they had three children: Nechama, Yitzhak, and Yisroel. He died in 2011.
    Avroham, in his late 40s, narrates his Irish-Catholic upbringing, his early encounters with Jewish people, and his conversion to Orthodox Judaism. He describes how the Lubavitch of the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn have changed and grown in the years since 1970, when he moved there. He reflects on the religious community's acceptance of him as a Christian convert, on how his children have grown up Lubavitch, and on secular Jews who take up Orthodox practice as adults (known as baal teshuvah). When asked, he explains the extent of his interaction with the Black residents of Crown Heights. At various points throughout the interview, he dwells on religious subjects: how boys and girls are educated, how Judaism is different from Christianity, how conversion for marriage is different than for faith alone, and others. Interview conducted by Jill Vexler.
    African Americans |x Relations with Jews; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x History |y 20th century; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Religious life and customs; Canadian Americans; Conversion |x Judaism; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Hasidim |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Interfaith families; Interfaith marriage |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Jewish religious education; Jews |x Return to Orthodox Judaism; Race relations -- United States; Sunset Park (New York, N.Y.); Crawford, Avroham; Congregation Lubavitch (Crown Heights, New York, N.Y.); Hecht, Jacob J.
  - Crawford, Nechama, Yisroel Crawford and Suri Crawford, 1993 August 25; 1994.006.06
    Nechama Crawford was raised in the Brooklyn neighborhood of Crown Heights. She attended a private Lubavitch school, Bais Rivkah, from kindergarten through twelfth grade. At her Bat Mitzvah (a Jewish coming-of-age ceremony that takes place at the age of twelve or thirteen), she read from the Genesis chapter chai Sarah, or "the life of Sarah." Her younger brother, Yisroel, attended Oholei Torah—a Lubavitch school that focuses on religious education and teaches exclusively in Hebrew and Yiddish—before switching to Lubavitch Yeshiva. Their mother, Suri, grew up in Holyoke, Massachusetts and had a Modern Orthodox upbringing among her Litvish (or Latvian Jewish) family.
    Nechama and Yisroel—respectively in twelfth and sixth grade at the time of the interview in 1993—talk about their experience growing up in the Lubavitch community of the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn. They describe the various forms of religious education and practice that exist within Hasidic Judaism, as well as the expectations and roles that are laid out for young girls and boys. At the interviewer's prompting, Nechama reflects on her community's relationship with the "outside," especially the Black residents of Crown Heights and the non-Jewish city at large. Suri, their mother, talks about her children's education, the role of women in her religion, the cost of living in Brooklyn, and her Modern Orthodox upbringing. Interview conducted by Jill Vexler.
    African Americans |x Relations with Jews; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x History |y 20th century; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Religious life and customs; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Hasidim |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Jewish religious education; Jewish women; Race relations -- United States; Teenagers |x Religious life; Cato, Gavin; Congregation Lubavitch (Crown Heights, New York, N.Y.); Crawford, Nechama; Crawford, Suri; Crawford, Yisroel
  - De Shong, Roxanne, 1993 August 29; 1994.006.07
    Roxanne De Shong was born in Saint Vincent and the Grenadines. She immigrated to Brooklyn in the 1970s with her parents to Crown Street in the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn. Her father sold life insurance and her mother worked near the family home at Woolworth's. She went to a public school in the East New York neighborhood of Brooklyn for one year, then to Holy Spirit Catholic School for grades two to eight. She attended Clara Barton High School and then Hostoffs in The Bronx. De Shong's major in high school was Dental Assistant and she worked at several offices in New York City. De Shong has more than one child, including a son. Her son's father was shot and killed in a drug-related incident in the Harlem neighborhood of Manhattan.